Guide to the Ventana Records TAM 121
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ventana Records
1982-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
TAM 121
6.5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 4 manuscript boxes, and 2 oversize flat boxes
Ventana was founded by cultural workers who had toured Nicaragua in June and July 1983. Its activities included cultural exchanges with the Sandinista Cultural Workers Association (ASTC), collection of cultural supplies for Nicaraguan arts organizations, and support of anti-war networks and coalitions. The collection contains flyers, brochures, clippings, newspapers, and posters.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without resriction with the exception of box 4. these materials are restricted to members of Ventana only or researchers with permission of the Ventana Executive Committee.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Ventana Collection was initiated by the Executive Committee of Ventana in late 1984 and the first papers officially received by the Tamiment Library on April 17, 1985. Additional materials were received in late 1987, 1988 and 1989. The accession number associated with this gift is 1984.010.
Arrangement
Files are arranged by subject.
Historical/Biographical Note
Ventana was founded by several individuals who had been with one of two delegations of cultural workers to tour Nicaragua in June and July 1983. The official structure and name was given in early 1984 with the participation of other more recently returned delegates (in particular, a delegation of theatre workers, Dec. 1983).
"We are North American artists and cultural workers who oppose United States intervention and destabilization efforts in Nicaragua, in Central America and the Caribbean. We support the people of the Americas in their right to self-determination and the right to govern in the interests of the majority of the people. Having witnessed the disastrous effects of U.S. foreign policy on the people of Nicaragua, we seek to change this policy through the use of our cultural skills and activities."
Activities since its founding include sending additional delegations, hosted by the Sandinista Cultural Workers Association (ASTC), hosting in NY well-known painters and performers from Nicaragua, collecting cultural supplies as material aid to Nicaraguan arts organizations, and participating in solidarity and anti-war networks and coalitions. Using their firsthand accounts, individual members have written articles, plays, novels, films, reports and editorial letters. (The most outstanding accomplishment in this respect is Ventana delegate Reed Brody's front-page report on contra atrocities). Others have incorporated their experiences into theatre and musical performances, sculpture, photography, and paintings. Many have shown slides to friends, colleagues, school programs, etc.
Scope and Content Note
The collection, as of July 1986, contains about 6 feet of records: flyers and brochures, newsclippings and newspapers, pamphlets, posters. Ventana receives these from returning delegations, mailings from other organizations, and individual donations. The ephemeral nature of much of the material will make this collection a valuable source of information about the wide range of activities in response to the U.S. policies toward Nicaragua. The documents from Nicaragua and reports by North American eyewitnesses provide sympathetic coverage and more accurate evidence of Nicaraguan reality than is generally available in the U.S. These include reports on the contra activities, the Miskitu Indians, the Nicaraguan elections, the history of the literacy campaign, and the trade unions.
Clippings (information artifacts); Political activists -- United States.; Posters.; Pamphlets.; Newspapers.; Fliers (printed matter); Central America |x History |y 1979-; Central America |x Social conditions.; Nicaragua |x History |y Revolution, 1979.; Pacifists.; Nicaragua. Ejercito Popular Sandinista
- Newsclippings and newspapers
  - Intercontinental Press; clippings and feature articles from Mother Jones, the NY Times, the Militant, East Village Eye, Village Voice, Daily News, 1984 American Poetry Review, and Union press coverage, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
- Documents from Nicaragua
  - Ministry of Education pamphlets, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Education in 4 years of revolution (in Spanish) Triumph in Literacy: 1981 (in Spanish), see box 7, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1.1)
  - INCINE (film institute) catalog of documentaries, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Campesino Theatre (two articles), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Los Muchachos (magazine for youth, 3 issues), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Supreme Electoral Council - douments include text of the electoral law, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Election - booklets from Nicaragua and from North American election observers, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Dawning of Nicaragua, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - History: reprint of article from Labor Defender, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Daniel Ortega: article from Current Biographies and transcript of May 1984 delegation's interview (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Trade Union statistics, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - La Chicharra (Casa Nicaragua), undated (Box 2, Folder 11.1)
- Solidarity Groups A-Z, Events, Reports, Newsletters
  - Agro-Nica, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - All-People Congress (APC/PAM), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - April Actions for Peace, Jobs and Justice, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - ARC-Nicaragua (photo project, 1985) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Artists Call, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Artists in Action, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Artmakers, Inc. (mural projects), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Arts for a New Nicaragua, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Brigades/Nicaragua Exchange and Int'l Work Brigades, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Brigadista Bulletin; Int'l Work Brigades flyers, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - CANTO (Seattle), undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Casa Nicaragua, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Comrades (El Salvador), undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - CISPES (committee in Support of the People of El Salvador, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Cultural Correspondence (Jim Murray...), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Educators Committee on Central America (curriculum plan), undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - El Salvador Link, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - EPOCA (Environmental Project on Central America), undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Friends for Jamaica, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Friends of Nicaraguan Culture (San Francisco), undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Guatemala - committee and others, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Labor groups in solidarity)Library Guild, union delegations,...), undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - LINKS (Central America Health Rights Network), undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Lower East Side Sister City Project, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - MADRE, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - New York Nicas (various groupings and joint events), undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Nicaragua Network (DC), undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Nicaragua Solidarity Network (NY region) includes NICANEWS, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Nicaragua Support (newsletter and flyers), undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Oxfam - Tools for Peace, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - TecNica, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Ventana (flyers, in the news, notices), undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Vietnam - 10th and 11th anniversaries, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Witness for Peace, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Women's Coalition against intervention in Central America, and others, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - XChange TV, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Solidarity Group and Events, miscellaneous by years:, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Resources:, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Art and Performance Resources, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Bibliographies, discographies, etc., undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Cultural Correspondence publications (arts activists directory), undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Fundraising items (t-shirts, coffee...), undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Material aid: 1984 Ministry of Culture "needs" list; 1986 ASTC list (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Tour groups (other than Ventana), undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Video & media work (various groups and events), undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Tour groups to Nicaragua (other than Ventana), undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Reports:, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - History (1927 Labor Defender article), undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Daniel Ortega - biographical info, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - "Witness for Peace - what we have seen and heard", undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Embargo info, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Reports by Ventana delegates, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Reports (Miskito Indians, Trade unions, Art), undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - US Violations against Nicaragua (Philly Lawyers Commte), undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Quixote Center reprints, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Women in Nicaragua - various reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Other reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Ventana Records
  Conditions Governing Access
  Internal recordds of Ventana are restricted to members only. Donor permission is required for access. Please contact the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu.
  - Correspondence, minutes, bylaws, delegations, finances, lists, undated (Box 4)
- Barricada
  - Barricada, undated (Box 5)
- Other Nicaraguan papers
  - Nicaraguan papers, undated (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Unprocessed
  - Materials to be added to Boxes 1, 2, and 5, 6, undated (Box 7)
- Posters
  - Posters from Nicaragua (literacy, map case health, history of the Revolution, culture, etc.) plastic FSLN banners, undated (Box 8)
- Restricted Material (Box 9)
  Materaials are closed.